University of Connecticut, Agricultural Economics Department Records
© 2010 University of Connecticut
Series II: Emergency Farm Labor Financial Records ( undated, 1941-1948 ) includes annual reports, budget requests, budget statements, financial statements, financial reports for the Agricultural Extension Division. There is information on the Extension Farm labor budget, memoranda on budget requests, receipts for 1942-1948. Also included are work contracts, including interstate workers, project agreements, voluntary agreement on standards of employment, recruiting labor memorandum agreements, termination of work agreement for Newfoundlanders, a supplement agreement for extension work, memoranda of agreement for Negro College workers, and extension agreements for extension workers. Memoranda of agreements and farm labor contracts for the Cooperative, statement of employment need, personnel files, personnel expense account lists, auditors certificates, accounting records of the Extension farm labor, account information for farm labor and farm labor accounting records as well as financial documentation, application for emergency purchases, wage information and wage hearing minutes, monthly state farm labor work camps, and wage rate hearings are also included in this Series.
Series III: Legislation ( undated, 1942-1947 ) includes all legislative action materials that would have had an effect on the State labor situation including a Senate Report on Farm Labor, Selective Service, and child labor. Minutes from Senate Appropriations committee hearings, printed Acts and Bills, House of Representative reports, Joint resolutions, and regulations are also included.
Series IV: Emergency Farm Labor Conferences ( 1942-1947 ) documents regional conference programs, and a State agricultural defense labor committee program.
Series V: Emergency Farm Labor Schematics ( undated, 1943 ) clearly show the complicated institutional hierarchy of the following organizations: the Connecticut organization for agricultural labor, Wartime activities, the organization of Extension Emergency Farm Labor Program and the USDA War Food Administration.
Series VI: Emergency Farm Labor Marketing Material ( undated, 1942-1949 ) includes newspaper clippings, bulletins, brochures, certification/merit badges, and magazine articles on Connecticut's Land Army. There is a publicity report by Paul Putnam, and a radio address script. There is a poem by James Young, a New London County Farm labor assistant and documentation on the War Food Administration movie to recruit Emergency Farm Labor with script, called "Victory Harvest." There are marketing posters from U.S. Crop Corps "Harvest War Crops" and "Crop emergency" (1944). Also included information regarding a Newfoundlanders supper and meeting, menu and attendees, plus Newfoundland motion pictures. Regarding Connecticut Light & Power Company, there is the text of an address made to the American Society of Agricultural Engineers regarding the farm labor problem. The purpose of the address was to as if electrically operated farm equipment could help production. Some obstacles to rural electrical service were noted. Also, a determination needed to be made regarding which jobs could have been made more efficient with electrical power equipment. For example, were there electrically operated machines for specific jobs? The address delineated three proposed phases: 1) determining the available electrical equipment; 2) encouraging farm invented and developed equipment; and 3) additional new devices.
Series VII: Reports ( 1943-1948 ) includes Emergency farm labor summary of accomplishments for 1945-1948, statistical summaries of the Agricultural Conservation program, and an Emergency Farm Labor statistical summary of worker placement. There are statistics on farm workers by ethnicity, a statistical report on agricultural marketing and farm transportation.
Series VIII: Farm Labor ( undated, 1939-1947 ) includes USDA surveys on outside agricultural labor requirements for 1947, USDA farm labor requirements for 1939, 1944, a USDA co-op work guide, a USDA migrant workers guide for 1947 and a USDA farm labor newsletter and committee report for 1943-1044. There is information on the Civilian War Service, the War Manpower Commission, and War Food Administration memoranda. Documentation on the Extension Services and the farm work camps, as well as the Connecticut Labor Department standards for tobacco workers is also included.
Series IX: Farm Labor Camp ( undated, 1943-1947 ) includes Emergency farm labor statistical summaries from 1943-1947, a Farm Labor Program fact sheet for 1946-1947 and a Plan of Work for 1947. There is a State Farm Labor Report and a Farm Labor Employment report as well as documents regarding work simplification. There is information on the Connecticut Agricultural Wartime production capacity and the War manpower Commission. This series includes county agent reports on Farm labor, a conference address on farm labor and a Department of Labor tobacco Inspection Report. There are also analyses of Questionnaires by Tobacco supervisor, a training manual and reports on the Connecticut Farm Labor Program as well as the Out-of-State Farm Labor Programs.
Series X: Youth Labor Camps ( undated, 1943-1947 ) includes reports on the Robinson farm labor camp (undated), the farm work camps, the farm labor camp summary by town. There are handwritten Farm labor camp notebooks from Paul Putnam, as well as oversized charts on farm labor camps reports and stats by town, including: tobacco work camp - Girls (1945), Tobacco work camp - Boys (1945), Fruit and vegetable work camps (1944-1945); County reports (1945-1947); Camps by town (1946-1947); County monthly reports (1947); Annual report material (1947); Federal Rural Land Use by County; Inventory of State Owned Land; Staff and Salaries for the Florida Farm Labor Camp (undated); and Selective service camp data. Finally there is information on the farm labor camps from the Connecticut Department of Health. The farm work camps reports include information on Bolton, poultry, and a class report with a good description of camps, including a bibliography. There are brochures on the camps and employee vital statistics. There is advertising claiming that Youth Labor camps "Help American Farmers save the world from Starvation."
Series XI: Women's Land Army ( 1942-1945 ) includes a WLA news bulletin, a report with employee information such as weight, height, ethnicity, and religion. There is a report on training personnel recruitment brochure. There blank certificates of completion and an transportation card. There are meeting minutes of the advisory board, Victory Farm Volunteers newsletter and a Report on the Victory Farm Volunteers dairy course and pickle program.
Series XII: Extension Services ( 1943 ) series includes information about the Cooperative extension work between the Agricultural and Home Economics department and the government.
Series XIII: USDA Farm Survey Notes ( undated, 1914-1917, 1921-1943 ): Quantification of farms as a business, including information such as farm size, acres tilled, crops harvested, and livestock owned, as well as family size, age of workers (invariably children of farmer) and number of years as a farmer. These surveys also include qualitative information such as level of education of the farmer, his wife and children; the family's nationality and race, and their standard of living. These are organized first by County, then by farmer.
Series XIV: State of Connecticut farm economics agricultural survey ( ) includes the surveys as well as workers association part time farming surveys.
Series XV: Federal and State marketing surveys ( ) including dairy, cold storage poultry, fruits and vegetables. There are farmers' exchange feed prices, and market reports. There is information on the Eastern Connecticut Poultry Producers (ECPP), the USDA fluid milk report, and the Southern New England Telephone business conditions survey report. This series includes marketing papers, marketing of fruits and vegetables by motor truck.
Series XVI: Connecticut Agricultural College ( ). Department files from the 1930s Agricultural school including an extension service milk marketing survey; questionnaires, and farm management reports. Conference information and Cooperative associations; and correspondence from the office of I.G. Davis, Professor of Agricultural Economics in the Extension Office, in Charge of Extension Work in Marketing. Agricultural department employee information and records, including the home economics administration and employee information. From the I.G. Davis/Department of Economics Administration, there is a secretary rolodex from 1930s. Press releases, and Scantic County, Massachusetts tree farms soil conservation service. Financial Records of the Connecticut Valley Tobacco Association.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University's history. See also Southern New England Telephone Company Records for information similar to that found in Series VI and XV and Connecticut Valley Tobacco Growers Association Records for materials similar to that found in Series XVI. For detailed information not available in this finding aid, please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Bibliography
Connecticut Agricultural College Bulletin, Vol 27, No. 4. Storrs, CT: Connecticut Agricultural College, February 1932.
University of Connecticut Bulletin, Vol. 37, No. 4. Storrs, CT: University of Connecticut, 1942-1943.
Connecticut State College Biennial reports. Storrs, CT: Connecticut State College, 1926 - 1934.
Stemmons, Walter. Connecticut Agricultural College - A History, Storrs:, CT: Connecticut Agricultural College, 1931.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Organizations:
Family Names:
Places:
Subjects:
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Publications.; Photographs.; Blueprints.; Maps.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Minutes.; Press releases.; Audio visual materials.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Photocopies.; Notes.; Drawings.; Sound recordings.; Lantern slides.; Microfilm.; Filmstrips.; Histories.; Abstracts.; Examinations.; Broadsides.; Organizational charts.; Questionnaires.; Surveys.
Occupations:
Functions:
Titles:
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The Department of Agricultural Economics transferred the papers in 1982.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Emergency Farm Labor Correspondence, 1942-1948
  - USDA Letters to State Directors of Extension, 1942-1948 (Box 1)
  - USDA Letters to State Farm Labor Supervisors, 1943-1947
  - Telegrams, 1943-1946
  - Mr. Woodward, Director of Extension, 1942-1944
  - Mr. Clapp, Acting Director of Extension 1945-1947
  - Federal War Office Memoranda, 1945
  - War Food Administration circular, 1945
  - Selective Service, 1943
- Series II: Emergency Farm Labor Financial Records, undated, 1941-1948
  - Annual Reports, 1943-1947 (Box 2)
  - Budget Requests, 1944-1947
  - Budget statements, 1943-1947
  - Financial statements, 1947
  - Financial report - Agricultural Extension Division, 1945-1947
  - Extension Farm Labor Budget, 1944-1946
  - Memoranda on budget requests, 1942-1948
  - Receipts, 1942-1944
  - Receipts, 1945-1948
  - Interstate workers contract, 1946-1947
  - Sample Farm Labor Project Agreement, undated
  - Voluntary agreement "standards of employment", undated
  - Recruiting labor memorandum agreement, 1947
  - Termination of work agreement - Newfoundlanders, 1946
  - Supplemental Agreement for Extension work, 1944
  - Memorandum of Agreement for Negro College workers, 1947
  - Extension of Agreement for Extension workers, 1945-1947
  - Memorandum of Agreement - Cooperative, 1943
  - Farm Labor Contract - Cooperative, 1943-1945
  - Employment needs, 1941, 1943, 1946-1947
  - Personnel files, 1942-1943, 1944-1946
  - Personnel expense account lists, undated
  - Auditors certificate, undated
  - Extension Farm Labor Accounting Records, 1946
  - Farm labor accounts, 1945-1947
  - Farm labor camps accounting records, undated
  - Farm labor financial documentation, undated
  - Application for Emergency purchases, 1946
  - Farm labor wages, 1943-1946
  - Wage hearing minutes, 1945, 1947
- Series III: Legislation, undated, 1942-1947
  - Senate Report on Farm Labor, 1943 (Box 2)
  - Selective Service, 1942
  - Policy on War Manpower Commission child labor, 1943
  - Hearings Senate Appropriations Committee, 1944
  - Joint resolution, 1944
  - House of Representatives report, 1944
  - Regulations - Labor and Transportation, undated
  - Acts, 1943-1947
  - Minutes, 1945
  - Bills--Federal and State, 1944, 1946-1947
- Series IV: Emergency Farm Labor Conferences, 1942-1947
  - Regional conference programs, 1943-1947 (Box 2)
  - State agriculture defense labor committee, 1942-1943
- Series V: Emergency Farm Labor Schematics, undated, 1943
  - Schematics, undated, 1943 (Box 2)
- Series VI: Emergency Farm Labor Marketing Material, undated, 1942-1949
  The subject of the clippings concerns the Farm Labor situation during World War II in Connecticut, and the University Extension Service's attempts to recruit and train Farm Labor during the War. Mr. Paul Putnam, State Farm Labor Director through the Extension Service under the Emergency Farm Labor organization, is the subject of many of these articles. The clippings tell a story of a State desperate to fill the labor gap left by the Selective Service. Many different groups were suggested as replacement labor, including prison labor (those arrested for public drunkenness). This method of supplying labor was considered unfeasible, and so new labor supplies were pursued.
  The second method of finding labor was to suggest the use of Massachusetts teenagers as farm labor. This proposal was attacked and defeated by Employment Department officials from Boston. The search for labor shifted to conscientious objectors, Japanese evacuees, and Southern (i.e. Afro-American) migrant laborers. These alternatives provided labor, however a new housing problem was created. Complaints from the white community surrounding the Labor Camps objected to having Afro- American migrant labor living in their community, although they were not quite so explicit. Various reasons were used to couch their protests in practical reasons, however one official is quoted in the clippings on the record as being of the opinion these were thinly veiled racist arguments.
  This problem was solved in part by the creation of Farm Labor Camps for various newly minted organizations: Victory Farm Volunteers, the Women's Land Army, high school boys and girls (all white). In addition, recruiting Newfoundlanders from Canada through an arrangement with their government proved mutually beneficial.
  Jamaica n farm laborers were also recruited for seasonal labor and there are many photographs in the newspaper clippings that show these men in the typical 1940s formal attire for train travel: hats, suits and ties; presumably to calm racial fears. There are additional photos of the Jamaican men's choir, and celebrations of their National Holiday. One revealing photo shows a racially mixed audience listening to the men's choir, a marketing attempt to show the community there would be no negative repercussions of having Afro-American and Jamaican men in their neighborhoods. In addition, there is an article written by a Jamaican farm worker, which gives a different perspective on the farm labor experience, and reveals culture differences between Jamaicans and Americans. This man describes his trip by boat from the West Indies in April and covers all of the impressions of this trip from the cold temperatures to his being unaccustomed to farm work, (he was an artisan at home). He writes that although the pay is high, the food is bad: only bacon and eggs served everyday. The Jamaicans were given a Field Day in honor of their National Holiday, which included soccer, cricket, boxing, racing, and dancing with the Nelson Orchestra. Finally, there is an article short on information and raises questions about how Jamaicans were treated. Describing the departure of some Jamaicans due to fear of winter, but also due to "bad treatment" one wonders exactly what their experience was like, and is a foreshadowing of the rioting mentioned below.
  The Woman's Land Army is the subject of articles that include photographs, many showing young women extolling the virtues of dairy farming over secretarial work. These ladies are quoted as describing dairying "fun" compared to "depressing" secretarial work, despite their self-described "handicap" of being weaker than men.
  Ultimately, the shortage of farm labor was solved by the recruitment of high school students from Florida, hired for "Vacation Work". There are many articles and photographs that chronicle this endeavor. There were glitches in the Farm Labor Camps, among the fewdocumented: sewage problems for Jamaican workers, the electrocution of female farm laborers trying to take a shower, and an incident of poor communication between young local workers and the transportation authorities which resulted in nine little girls (all around 14 years old) walking 21 miles home to Hartford. This incident was widely reported, and many of the articles are included here.
  The marketing campaign is evident in the articles on radio addresses by the Extension Service, many of which are described in these articles. In addition, there are editorials interspersed which weigh in on almost all of these topics.
  There is extensive documentation of the child labor issue; the debate over whether it should be illegal to hire children under 14 for farm labor. Mr. Paul Putnam, State Farm Labor Supervisor under the Extension Service's Emergency Farm Labor Program of the University of Connecticut, was key in defeating this child labor legislation, essentially making it legal to hire children under 14, with no consequences for the company if being found doing so. As an appeasement, Mr. Putnam brokered a "voluntary agreement" for the tobacco industry to agree to not hire those 14 and under. It should not come as a surprise to find that there continued to be documentation of children as young as 11 years old working 8 hour days, 6 days a week with no consequences for their employers.
  One of the interesting facts that come from the articles is the land-ownership distribution in Connecticut. The Extension Service was no longer necessarily helping the individual farmer when the statistics are published that, "Queen Wilhelmina of Holland was declared to be one of the largest owners of tobacco land in the Enfield section of Connecticut, she visits to inspect her holdings". That the Extension Service was working to provide labor for tobacco companies leasing from Queen Wilhelmina illustrates the difference between their stated goals in the Bulletins and the practical realities of their endeavors.
  There are eye-catching photographs from the coverage of the last day of work for Floridian high school students who have a Field Day to celebrate the end of their working summer. Headlines proclaim the Floridian Winner of the Shade Tobacco Queen beauty contest, for which Paul Putnam was a judge. However, even the beauty contest was subject to the political and economic ties between the Extension Service and industry, "Ann Flora was disqualified for first place because she was not an employee of the Connecticut Shade Tobacco Growers Association". The field day also had softball games, swimming, worker prizes, and dancing in the evening. Interestingly, this article makes it clear that the brochures found in the Marketing series of this collection shows these activities as part of the Vacation Work experience, in reality is only recording one day of these recreations per summer. These brochures clearly exclude references to and photographs of the daily grind of work. For the non-white laborers, a "Field Day" was held on a different day, segregated from the white Floridian workers. These events included winners in a seven-event contest held Sunday evening at Hartman farm specifically for Jamaican and southern "Negro" [sic] tobacco workers to play checkers, dominoes, and have contests such as basket foul shooting and a sprint. There are no photographs from this event.
  The abuses on farm labor camps follow a specific pattern in this collection. First, there are reports of abuse, and in response there are articles that describe the official reaction: invariably, a tour of the offending facility for the benefit of various religious and legislative leaders. For example, there is a single article about Bahamian and Jamaican workers who rioted, although the article fails to indicate what conditions they were living in. In reaction to this bad press, a Farm labor camp held an "Open House" for 12 local community leaders who visited with campers, stayed for dinner, and had entertainment and a tour. Quotes about how well-run the labor camp was give no indication the situation of the Bahamian and Jamaican workers was resolved.
  Articles clearly serving as marketing tools include headlines such as, "Life on state tobacco farm not all hard labor" and are accompanied by photos of kids eating, playing badminton, playing softball, and swimmers curiously have hair which is both dry and styled. Another article headline advertises, "High school lassies work and play. Summer work on a tobacco farm is like a vacation, except you get paid".
  Pay is an interesting subject, this article indicates high school students earn 45 cents and hour, which adds up to $100 for the whole summer after room and board is deducted. This total is achieved by working 8 hour days, 6 days a week, which hardly includes swimming, badminton or softball. Comparing these articles to the Farm Labor Camp reports in this collection that describe daily schedules beginning at 5 a.m. gives insight into the discrepancies between the actual program and the marketing campaign the public saw.
  - Emergency Farm Labor Newspaper Clippings, 1942, 1943-1947 (Box 2)
  - Food for Freedom survey, undated
  - Marketing Bulletins, 1949
  - Brochures, undated, 1943-1946
  - Extension Service Marketing Brochure "Vacation Work", undated
  - Articles on Connecticut's Land Army, 1942-1943, 1945-1946
  - Putnam publicity report, 1946
  - Radio Script, 1947
  - Poem, 1944
  - Press releases, 1943, 1946, 1948
  - War Food Admininstration movie, 1945
  - Posters, 1944
  - Newfoundlanders Supper and Meeting, 1947
  - Connecticut Light & Power Company, 1945
- Series VII: Reports, 1943-1948
  - EFL Summary of accomplishments, 1945-1948 (Box 3)
  - Statistical summary of the agricultural conservation program, 1948
  - EFL stat summary of worker placement, 1943-1947
  - Statistics on farm workers by ethnicity, 1943
  - Statistical report on agricultural marketing, 1946
  - Farm Transportation, 1945-1947
  - Statistical summaries, undated (Box 4)
  - Committees, 1939-1947
- Series VIII: Farm Labor, undated, 1939-1947
  - USDA survey on outside agricultural labor req, 1947 (Box 3)
  - USDA farm labor requirements, 1939, 1944
  - USDA co-op work guide, undated
  - USDA migrant workers guide, 1947
  - USDA farm labor newsletter/committee report, 1943-1944
  - Civilian War Service, 1943-1944
  - War Manpower, 1942-1944
  - War Food Administration memoranda, 1944
  - Extension Services, 1944-1947
  - Report on farm work camps, 1945
  - Report on farm work camps, 1944
  - Connecticut Labor Department standards for tobacco workers, 1942
- Series IX: Farm Labor Camp, undated, 1943-1947
  - EFL farm labor statistical summary, 1943-1947 (Box 3)
  - Farm Labor Program fact sheet, 1946-1947
  - Plan of Work, 1947